Finding Aid for Stanley S. Kresge Papers 1909-1985
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Stanley S. Kresge Papers 1909-1985
Kresge, Stanley Sebastian, 1900-
8 film reels
0.5 linear feet papers not microfilmed
1 oversize folders
2 oversize volumes
20 microfilms 10.5 linear
Businessman with the S. S. Kresge Company (later K mart Corporation) and philanthropist. Business records, materials relating to philanthropic activities, notably documenting the work of the Kresge Foundation, and family materials; also organizational materials, speeches, and photographs and motion pictures.
86992 Aa/2; AC; UAm
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Dorothy Kresge (Donor No. 6888 ) in November, 1985.
The collection is open for research, except where noted.
A.H. Taylor, Jr., President of the Kresge Foundation, described Stanley Kresge in the Oakland Press on August 8, 1982, "He's one of a vanishing breed. He came through an entrepreneur background. He's close to a self-made man and credits first the Lord, and second his Dad."
Stanley Kresge was born in Detroit on June 11, 1900, the eldest son of Anna and Sebastian Kresge. His devoutly Christian parents and his own active involvement with the church from an early age led to the development of the moral principles which guided his life. He rose to leadership positions in both the S.S. Kresge Company (later K mart Corporation), and Kresge Foundation, organizations that were established by his father Sebastian.
Stanley's first experience in the retailing business was in the stockroom of the Kresge store in Detroit during summer vacations. After graduating from Detroit Central High School in 1918, he attended the University of Michigan for three years before transferring to Albion College, where he received his A.B. Degree in 1923. In that same year he began his full-time involvement with his father's growing company. He served as a manager-trainee in the Detroit store at Grand River and Woodward where he learned the business by working in the stockroom, and as a buyer and floor manager. He became assistant manager and later merchandise manager of the store. In 1926, Stanley moved to Flint as assistant manager of the Kresge store, and a year later he was promoted to manager of the new Kresge Dollar Store in Detroit at Grand River and Joy Road.
In 1930, Stanley joined the headquarters staff of the Kresge Company and for the next twenty years worked in a variety of positions, primarily related to sales promotion. He was appointed to the Board of Directors in 1950, became vice-chairman of the Board in 1953, and succeeded his father as chairman in 1966, shortly before his father died.
Stanley resigned his position as Kresge chairman in 1967, to become chairman of the Kresge Foundation, a philanthropic organization founded by his father in 1924, of which Stanley had been president since 1952. He was named honorary chairman in 1978 and remained actively involved with the Foundation thereafter.
In addition to his work with the Kresge Company and the Foundation, Stanley was active in religious, educational, political, and civic organizations. He was a longtime member of the Metropolitan United Methodist Church of Detroit and served as a trustee; he was involved in the affairs of Albion College, where he also was a trustee; he was a board member of the Greater Detroit YMCA; he participated in Detroit Rotary Club events; and he was active in the Fellowship of Christian Athletes. Kresge's hobbies included photography, book collecting, and sports--he had played baseball and football in high school and college, and enjoyed playing tennis for much of his life.
It was on the tennis courts of the Metropolitan United Methodist Church of Detroit that he met his future wife, Dorothy McVittie, in 1915. They courted for eight years and married in 1923. They maintained two residences, one in Detroit and one in Lake Angelus, but later in life the Kresges made their permanent home in Lake Angelus. They had three sons, fifteen grandchildren, and eleven great-grandchildren. Stanley Kresge died on June 30, 1985.
The Stanley Kresge Papers, an important source for the researcher interested in the history of the S.S. Kresge Company/K mart Corporation; the work of the Kresge Foundation; and the Kresge family, have been divided into six series: Kresge Company/K mart Corporation; Kresge Foundation; Organizations; Personal; Speeches; and Visual Materials. The collection has now been microfilmed to allow inter-library access to the collection. These 21 microfilm rolls comprise the bulk of Kresge's collection. Excluded from the microfilming have been a few folders of restricted financial materials, two oversize ledgers, and, of course, the motion picture films. The following finding aid is a guide to the entire collection with appropriate indication of files and other materials not part of the microfilm edition.
Subjects:
Business records.; K-Mart Corporation.; Kresge Foundation.; Philanthropists--Michigan.; Retail trade.; S.S. Kresge Company.; Kresge, Stanley Sebastian, 1900-; Kresge, Sebastian Spering, 1867-1966.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Albion College.; Art.; Beta Theta Pi. Lambda Chapter (University of Michigan); Business enterprises.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Detroit.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Iron Mountain.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Marquette.; Detroit (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Football.; Fraternities and sororities.; Graham, Billy, 1918-; Iron Mountain (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; K-Mart Corporation.; Kresge, Sebastian Spering, 1867-1966.; Kresge, Stanley Sebastian, 1900-; Kresge family.; Kresge Foundation.; Marquette (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; University of Michigan--Football.; University of Michigan--Bands.
Genre/Form:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.
- Kresge Company/K Mart Corporation
  The Kresge Company/K mart Corporation series consists of those materials collected and generated by Stanley during his 43 years of experience in retailing. It measures four linear feet and is arranged alphabetically by topic. There is much that will interest the researcher, including the background files, which contain materials on the history of both S.S. Kresge as well as other retailing firms, and transcripts of conversations between Stanley and several company executives regarding their early experiences with the company and its founder. There are numerous financial reports (including reports for S.S. Kresge Company, Ltd., of Canada, and Mount Clemens Pottery); committee reports; materials relating to company employees, including newsletters and employee relation policies and guidelines; and documents which provide valuable insight into the role of Kresge store managers. Among the latter are convention reports, and "general letters" from the 1930s which were sent from headquarters to store managers to guide them in their day-to-day operations. The contents list for this portion of the Stanley Kresge Papers is quite detailed, to assist the researcher in locating specific materials.
  - Background/History, 3 folders (Reel 1)
  - Anniversary Congratulations (Reel 1)
    (letters to Stanley re: his career with Kresge/K mart)
  - Board of Directors
    - Mailings 1966 (Reel 1)
      (mostly financial reports sent out to directors)
    - Meetings and Reports
      - 1947, 1949 (Reel 1)
      - 1952 (Reel 1)
      - 1960-1961 (Reel 1)
      - 1968-1969 (Reel 1)
      - 1970 (Reel 1)
      - 1971 (Reel 2)
      - 1972 (Reel 2)
      - 1973 (Reel 2)
      - 1974 (Reel 2)
      - 1975 (Reel 2)
      - 1976 (Reel 2)
  - Bylaws 1920s-1970s (Reel 2)
  - Clippings 1923-1984, 3 folders (Reel 2)
  - Common Stock: (Reel 2)
    (1921 correspondence; printed materials on Kresge stock; 1968 announcement materials on 3 for 1 split)
  - Competition (Reel 2)
    (miscellaneous reports on competitors 1949 and 1954 and S.S. Kresge President Harry Cunningham, "Random Thoughts...," 1961 corporate reports, 1972-1973)
  - Complaints 1960s (Reel 2)
    (miscellaneous reports, correspondence on customer complaints)
  - Construction Department 1949 (Reel 2)
    (memo on departmental organization)
  - Customer Service Campaign (Reel 2)
    (1939 cassette recording of greetings from Kresge executives "on the occasion of the September Friendly Service Campaign"; and Friendly Service saleswoman training pamphlets, undated)
  - Departmental Sales: K mart, special report 1964 (Reel 2)
  - Depression, The:1930s (Reel 2)
    (memo by C.B. Tuttle, "Proposal of Merrill, Lynch & Company regarding support of Kresge stock")
  - Directories: personnel and stores, 5 folders (Reel 3)
    (Includes 1970s store locations map and 1920s and 1970s Who's Who In The Kresge Organization)
  - Directories: personnel and stores, 5 folders (Reel 4)
    (continued)
  - Employees
    - Announcements 1950s-1980s (Reel 4)
    - Minority Hiring (Reel 4)
      (Detroit Urban League summary of blacks employed in retail outlets in Detroit, undated; statement on need for integrated retail store work forces, undated, no author; announcement of minority board of directors appointment, 1975)
    - Newsletter 1919, 1929, 1950s-1980s, 2 folders (Reel 4)
    - Relations 1949 (Reel 5)
      (includes vacation, recognition, career opportunity, and pension materials; and "Pocket Guide to Employee Relations")
  - Executive Committee (Reel 5)
    (includes interesting correspondence and memos re: Kresge stock in early 1930s also scattered committee memos, minutes, reports 1930s-1960s, correspondence from Howard Baldwin to Sebastian Kresge re: committee meetings happenings 1950s)
  - Expense Statement: Kresge Company, "Overhead Department Expense Statement,12-31-54, " (Reel 5)
  - Fair, The 1940s-1950s (Reel 5)
  - Fiftieth Anniversary, 1949/Fiftieth Annual Meeting 1962 (Reel 5)
    (mostly promotional and congratulatory materials, includes clippings)
  - Financial Analysis 1945-1954 with gaps (Reel 5)
    (includes "Reports and Accounts," sales reports, correspondence)
  - Financial Officer Authority 1973 (Resolution) (Reel 5)
  - Financial Statements
    - 1914-1919 (Reel 5)
    - 1920-1923 (Reel 5)
    - 1927-1928, 1932 (Reel 5)
    - 1948-1949 (Reel 5)
    - 1950 (Reel 5)
    - 1952 (Reel 5)
    - 1954-1960 (with gaps) (Reel 5)
    - 1961-1963 (Reel 6)
    - 1966-1970 (Reel 6)
  - General Ledger 1909-1912 (Volume 1)
    (Not Microfilmed)
  - Journal 1909-1912 (Volume 2)
  - Kresge-Newark 1952-1953 (Reel 6)
    (financial statements and correspondence from Howard and William Baldwin to Sebastian Kresge re: managerial matters and possible sale of company)
  - Kresge Realty Company 1923, 1926-1928 (financial statements) (Reel 6)
  - Kresge and Wilson Company undated, 1906, 1908 (Reel 6)
    (early financial records)
  - Managers
    - Conventions: report; 1916; program, 1920; Stanley's notes, 1932 (Reel 6)
    - General Letters
      (from headquarters to store managers re: inventory, merchandising, personnel, policies)
      - 1931-1932, 2 folders (Reel 6)
      - 1933-1934 (Reel 6)
      - 1935 (Reel 6)
      - 1936 (Reel 6)
      - 1937 (Reel 6)
      - June 1939 (Reel 7)
  - Mergers (Reel 7)
    (office memo, H.B. Cunningham to Stanley, discussing undesirability of merger with Interstate Department Stores, 1962 correspondence re: merger with Kress, 1955-1960)
  - Mt. Clemens Pottery: miscellaneous, including financial statements 1926, 1927, 1948, 1954 (Reel 7)
  - Name Change 1977 (Reel 7)
    (correspondence; includes Cunningham to Stanley memo re: the necessity of the change to "K mart Corporation," and letters from Stanley to board of Directors members protesting the change)
  - News Release 1980s (Reel 7)
  - Operating Committee: Stanley's notes 1947-1952, reports and minutes, 1952 (Reel 7)
  - Organization Plan: "Report on Suggested Plan of Organization, December 19, 1919" (Reel 7)
  - Political Campaigns 1938, 1940 (Reel 7)
    (memos, from C.B. Tuttle, Trustee, re: campaign contributions)
  - S.S. Kresge Company Limited 1930s-1970s, mostly from, 1950s (Reel 7)
    (includes miscellaneous financial statements, memos on personnel matters, Board of Directors minutes and by-laws)
  - Self-Service Operations 1954 (Reel 7)
    (memo, Cunningham to Kresge, et al, describing/assessing a Woolworth self-service store in Pennsylvania)
  - Stockholders: mostly lists 1950s, miscellaneous correspondence, Stanley to/from stockholders, 1950s-1960s (Reel 7)
  - Stock Option Plans undated (mostly descriptions) (Reel 7)
  - Stores
    - Acquisitions: undated list, "Stores Acquired by Purchase by S.S. Kresge up to 1912," (Reel 7)
    - Business Activity undated, 1948 (Box 4)
      (summaries by store)
    - Openings, Closings, Regional Transfers: plot and store plans 1938, 1959 announcements of, 1970s mostly, 1980s (Reel 8)
    - Opening Sales 1959-1973 (Reel 8)
    - Operating Statements 1951-1952 (Reel 8)
    - Policies: manuals undated, 1962 (Reel 8)
    - Store Development Committee: Stanley's handwritten notes from meetings 1950-1956; information on store losses for, 1959-1960 (Reel 8)
  - Sunday Selling: mostly letters of complaint to Stanley and his responses 1958, 1961, 1962, 1964 (Reel 8)
  - Superintendents
    - Job Guidelines/Instructions manual undated (Reel 8)
    - Meetings/Conventions (Reel 8)
      (Stanley's notes 1948; Stanley's remarks, 1955 "Executive Presentation" book, manual 1956)
  - World War II, Restrictions and Rationings (Reel 8)
    (mostly headquarter memos to store managers)
  - Miscellaneous (Reel 8)
- Kresge Foundation
  The Kresge Foundation series is one linear foot, and from it the researcher will learn of the Foundation's specific activities in various fields. The background files provide information on the history of the organization, while the Annual Reports for the years 1924-1973 and Stanley's general files, arranged by decade for the years 1930-1985, trace the Foundation's endowments to specific groups and organizations. The general files contain a variety of materials including financial statements, trustee memos, and minutes from meetings. The minutes are helpful in learning what the trustees did and how they worked, but shed little light on why applications for grants were accepted or rejected. Access to grant applications is restricted.
  - Background (Reel 8)
    (includes speeches by Stanley on the policies and work of the Foundation)
  - Annual Reports (Box 4)
    - Volume 1 1924-1966 (Box 4)
    - Volume 2 1967-1973 (Box 4)
  - Clippings (Reel 8)
  - General
    - 1930s (Reel 8)
    - 1940s (Reel 8)
    - 1950s, 1960s (Reel 9)
    - 1970s (Reel 9)
    - 1980s, 2 folders (Reel 9)
  - Grant Requests 1980s (Box 4)
    [Restricted access]
- Organizations
  The Organizations series is two linear feet and arranged alphabetically by organization name. These are almost all organizations to which Stanley contributed time or money. This series reveals the breadth of Kresge's interests in and depth of commitment to religious and educational organizations and institutions, and of the friendships that arose from his interests, including those with the Reverend Billy Graham and Dr. Norman Vincent Peale. The researcher will also find materials which assist in documenting his contributions to the state and national Republican party.
  - Albion College
    - General
      - 1930s, 1940s (Reel 9)
      - 1950s (Reel 9)
      - 1960s-1980s (Reel 9)
    - Alumni Club 1939-1942 (Reel 9)
    - President (Whitehouse, William Whitcomb)
      - 1940s (Reel 9)
      - 1950s, 2 folders (Reel 9)
      - 1960s-1980s (Reel 9)
  - Foundation For Christian Living: Norman Vincent Peale 1940s-1980s, 2 folders (Reel 10)
  - Graham (Billy) Crusade 1950s-1980s (Reel 10)
  - Interlochen National Music Camp 1940s, 1950s (Reel 10)
  - Kresge House of Prayer 1970s (Reel 10)
  - Miner (Jack) Migratory Bird Foundation 1940s-1970s, 3 folders (Reel 10)
  - Mustard Seed, private mission in Taiwan 1970s, 1980s (Reel 10)
  - Prison Fellowship, Charles Colson 1970s, 1980s (Reel 11)
  - Republican Party 1940s-1980s, 2 folders (Reel 11)
  - Roberts Wesleyan College 1970s, 1980s (Reel 11)
  - Scarritt College 1970s (Reel 11)
  - Spring Arbor College 1970s, 1980s (Reel 11)
  - Starr Commonwealth 1950s-1970s (Reel 11)
  - Stony Brook School 1970s, 1980s (Reel 11)
  - William Tyndale College 1970s, 1980s (Reel 11)
  - Whorf, Inc., Mike, radio program 1970s (Reel 11)
  - Young Mens' Christian Association
    - General 1910s, 1960s-1980s (Reel 11)
    - Metropolitan Detroit, Board of Directors 1960s-1980s, 1 folders
      - Metropolitan Detroit, Board of Directors 1960s-1980s, 2 folders (Reel 12)
  - Miscellaneous (Reel 12)
- Personal
  The Personal series measures three and one-half linear feet, is arranged topically, and provides the greatest amount of information on Kresge family members. The background files will assist the researcher in detailing Stanley's corporate career and involvement with outside organizations. The bulk of the series is comprised of "correspondence," arranged by month and year, between Stanley and family members and friends. In the correspondence with family members, the most important is that with his mother, Anna Kresge; his wife, Dorothy; and his father, Sebastian. There is little material available on Anna Kresge, who was an important influence on Stanley as he grew up. The personal nature of the correspondence between mother and son is valuable in documenting their close relationship. From the correspondence with Dorothy (incoming only) one learns a good deal about the couple's personalities and their strong marriage. Finally, the correspondence with Sebastian not only assists in understanding their father-son relationship, but it is also important for the researcher interested in Kresge/K mart history. Quite often in their letters to one another, they would comment on important business developments.
  The correspondence with friends acquaints the researcher with many of Stanley and Dorothy's life-long friends. Because of their wide circle of friends and many activities, the Kresges could not correspond as frequently as they desired. Their letters, therefore, are often summaries of their activities and can provide the researcher with an overview of their more important personal and civic activities.
  The "religious organizations" sequence of the Personal series primarily documents Stanley's involvement with the Metropolitan United Methodist Church in Detroit. There are organizational materials on one of the largest Methodist churches in the country, and particularly interesting documents on Stanley's work with the Pastoral Relations Committee and its efforts to secure a new pastor for the church in 1943, when it sought Norman Vincent Peale, and in 1961. In 1943, Stanley's efforts included writing letters to Kresge managers in towns in which prospective candidates preached, requesting general information, and for 1961, there is a revealing memo from Stanley to other committee members describing his trip to meet one of the candidates.
  - Background, 3 folders (Reel 12)
  - Correspondence
    - Family
      - Kresge, Anna 1920s-1940s (Reel 12)
        (mother of Stanley)
      - Kresge, Dorothy
        (wife of Stanley; incoming letters only)
        - Undated (Reel 12)
        - 1921 (Reel 12)
        - 1922 (Reel 12)
        - 1923 (Reel 12)
        - 1924-1926 (Reel 13)
        - 1927 (Reel 13)
        - 1928 (Reel 13)
        - 1929-1938 (Reel 13)
      - Kresge, Sebastian
        (father of Stanley)
        - Undated, 1919, 1922, 1924 (Reel 13)
        - 1925-1929 (Reel 13)
        - 1930-1934 (Reel 13)
        - 1935-1939 (Reel 13)
        - 1940-1941 (Reel 13)
        - 1942-1943 (Reel 13)
        - 1944-1945 (Reel 14)
        - 1946 (Reel 14)
        - 1947 (Reel 14)
        - 1948 (Reel 14)
        - 1949 (Reel 14)
        - 1950 (Reel 14)
        - 1951 (Reel 15)
        - 1952 (Reel 15)
        - 1953 (Reel 15)
        - 1954 (Reel 15)
        - 1955 (Reel 15)
        - 1956 (Reel 16)
        - 1957 (Reel 16)
        - 1958 (Reel 16)
        - 1959 (Reel 16)
        - 1960 (Reel 16)
        - 1961 (Reel 17)
        - 1962 (Reel 17)
        - 1963 (Reel 17)
        - 1964-1966 (Reel 17)
      - Other Family Members 1924-1939 (Reel 17)
    - Friends
      - Blakemore, Howard (Reel 17)
      - Campbell, Scott and Heidi (Reel 17)
      - Carlisle, Russell and Betty (Reel 17)
      - Jones, Edgar (Reel 17)
      - Kim, Dr. Billy (Reel 17)
      - Penney, J.C. and Caroline (Reel 17)
      - Pierce, Robert Bruce (Reel 17)
      - Polling, Dr. Daniel (Reel 17)
      - Ream, G. Franklin (Reel 18)
      - Rice, Dr. Allen B., 2 folders (Reel 18)
      - Robbins, Omer (Reel 18)
      - Shaw, W.C (Reel 18)
      - Spratt, Elliott (Reel 18)
      - Waxer, Eddie (Reel 18)
      - Others, 2 folders (Reel 18)
  - Kresge, Anna: trust agreement 1924 correspondence re: her estate, 1952 (Reel 19)
  - Oil Well, 1950s-1970s, 2 folders (Reel 19)
    (correspondence re: Stanley's investment in an oil well)
  - Religious Organizations
    - Metropolitan Methodist Church of Detroit
      - General
        - 1945-1951 (Reel 19)
        - 1952-1955 (Reel 19)
        - 1956-1958 (Reel 19)
        - 1959-1963 (Reel 19)
        - 1964-1985 (Reel 19)
      - Paul Hickey Class 1950s-1960s (Reel 19)
        (married couples class)
      - Pastoral Relations Committee 1940s, 1960s, 1980s (Reel 19)
      - Quick, Dr. William 1980s (Reel 20)
    - Miscellaneous (Reel 20)
  - Stock Transactions: buy/sell orders 1930s (Box 11)
    (Not microfilmed)
- Speeches
  The Speeches series is one half linear foot and is organized alphabetically by name of organization to which the speech was made. They were primarily commencement, dedication, and dinner speeches and cover a variety of topics, including the influence of religion on businessmen, the value of education, the history and activities of the Kresge Foundation, and the opportunities available in retailing.
  - Alaska Methodist University 1968 (Reel 20)
  - Allied Youth International Conference 1960 (Reel 20)
  - Baker University 1955, 1961 (Reel 20)
  - Ball State University 1967 (Reel 20)
  - Bay View, Michigan 1953 (Reel 20)
  - Bethany College
    - 1959 (Reel 20)
    - 1960 (Reel 20)
  - Bethel College 1957 (Reel 20)
  - Cedar Campus 1956 (Reel 20)
  - DePauw University 1959 (Reel 20)
  - Detroit Bible College 1963 (Reel 20)
  - Detroit Historical Museum 1968 (Reel 20)
  - Distributive Education Clubs of America 1959 (Reel 20)
  - Farmington Senior High School 1960 (Reel 20)
  - Fuller Theological Seminary 1964 (Reel 20)
  - General Motors Institute 1964 (Reel 20)
  - Highland Park Rotary 1960 (Reel 20)
  - Hillsdale College 1971 (Reel 20)
  - Hope College 1959 (Reel 20)
  - Illinois Wesleyan University 1965 (Reel 20)
  - Interlochen Arts Academy 1962 (Reel 20)
  - Lansing Rotary Club 1968 (Reel 20)
  - Lincoln Memorial University 1969 (Reel 20)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology undated (Reel 20)
  - Metropolitan Methodist Church 1968 (Reel 20)
  - Michigan State College 1955 (Reel 20)
  - Michigan State University 1959 (Reel 20)
  - Morehouse College 1958 (Reel 20)
  - Notre Dame, University of 1973 (Reel 20)
  - Park Ridge, Illinois, First Methodist Church 1967 (Reel 20)
  - Pine Rest Hospital 1963 (Reel 20)
  - Quincy Council of Churches 1964 (Reel 20)
  - Roberts Wesleyan College 1971 (Reel 20)
  - St. James Methodist Church, Detroit 1967 (Reel 20)
  - Simpson College 1956, 1957 (Reel 20)
  - Spring Arbor College 1968 (Reel 20)
  - Starr Commonwealth for Boys 1961 (Reel 20)
  - Sweet Briar College 1958 (Reel 20)
  - Taylor University 1958 (Reel 20)
  - University of Michigan
    - 1961 (Reel 20)
    - 1963 (Reel 20)
  - Miscellaneous (Reel 20)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series consists of photographs and motion pictures.
  - Photographs